Finding Aid for Humphry and Moses Marshall Papers
William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
Humphry and Moses Marshall papers 1721-1863
Marshall, Humphry and Moses papers
Marshall, Humphry, 1722-1801 and Marshall, Moses, 1758-1813
1.25 linear feet
wclmss001347
The Humphry and Moses Marshall papers primarily document the careers of botanist Humphry Marshall and his nephew and business associate, Moses Marshall.
William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
1990, 1999. M-2549; M-4048.
The collection is open for research.
Biography
Humphry Marshall
Humphry Marshall was born in West Bradford, Pennsylvania, in 1722, the eighth child of Abraham and Mary Hunt Marshall. His parents, Quaker immigrants from Derbyshire, England, provided him with only a rudimentary English education, which ceased altogether at age 12, when he was apprenticed to a stonemason. However, from very early in life, Marshall was drawn to the study of natural history and continued his education on his own, reading widely. With the encouragement of his cousin, the botanist John Bartram, Marshall developed considerable practical skill in botany and natural history, and began to cultivate friendships with other scientists in America and abroad in the 1750s. Eventually, his correspondents included the British botanists John Fothergill, Peter Collinson, Sir Joseph Banks, and John Coakley Lettsom; the American scientists Thomas Parke, Benjamin Franklin, George Logan, Joseph Storrs, Timothy Pickering, John Dickinson, and Caspar Wistar; and French scientists and plant collectors including Michel-Guillaume St. Jean de Crèvecoeur, the Comtesse de Tesse, and Conrad-Alexandre Gérard; a number of German, Dutch, Swedish and Irish plant collectors and scientists.
In 1748, Marshall married Sarah Pennock (ca.1720-1766) and took up the management of his father's farm near the west branch of the Brandywine River. During the next few years, his time was largely consumed by farming; however, he continued to use free moments to pursue his botanical research. By the late 1750s, he began to exchange locally collected specimens with natural historians in other parts of the country and Great Britain, receiving scientific equipment, books, exotic specimens, money, or marketable goods such as linen in exchange. By 1764, when he began a major enlargement of his father's farmhouse, his botanical work had advanced to a stage that, necessitated his adding a conservatory for the culture of rare plants, probably the first such structure in Chester County.
Upon the death of his father in 1767, Marshall was left a substantial inheritance, enabling him to concentrate more time and resources on his botanical work. By this time, his correspondence with the British botanist, John Fothergill, had developed into an especially fruitful relationship, for Fothergill not only encouraged Marshall to collect plants beyond the confines of Chester County, but he paid well for Marshall's efforts. Equally important, Fothergill helped introduce Marshall to other botanists and plant collectors who had the resources to pay for American plants. Within a few years, Marshall found that he could depend almost entirely on horticulture and plant collecting for his income. His business expanded rapidly by means of a network of relationships established through family members, fellow Quakers, and fellow scientists.
In 1772, Marshall established a botanical garden on his estate, stocking it with herbaceous and arboreal representatives of the local flora and as many exotic plants as he could obtain from other parts of the nation and Europe. The following year, he began the construction of a new house adjacent to the garden, handling all phases of the construction by himself, and in that year, he was selected as a trustee of the General Loan Office. Despite pro-Independence sentiments, including long-standing support for the non-importation agreements, Marshall was in a precarious position as a pacifist and Quaker during the early days of the Revolution. He carefully monitored the events of the war as they unfolded, and was himself caught up when, in 1777, the Trustees of the Loan Office resigned as a body. Under the leadership of Samuel Preston Moore, the Trustees felt that to remain true to their affirmations that they would carry out the business of the crown, they should resign rather than follow the new laws.
Marshall's publishing career included contributions on tortoises, sunspots, and agriculture, but he is most remembered for Abrustrum Americanum (1785), the first botanical treatise written by a native American on American plants, produced in America. Despite slow sales in the United States, its use of Linnaean taxonomic nomenclature (though the plants are arranged alphabetically in the text) considerably enhanced Marshall's reputation among his European clientele. His scientific work and service to the scientific community earned Marshall honorary memberships in the Philadelphia Society for Promoting Agriculture and the American Philosophical Society.
Following the death of his first wife, Marshall married Margaret Minshall (1744-1823) in 1788. Neither marriage produced children. In the last two years of his life, his vision was greatly impaired by cataracts, for which he underwent an apparently unsuccessful surgery. He died in 1801 and was buried at Bradford Meeting House.
Moses Marshall
Moses Marshall was born in West Bradford, Pennsylvania, on November 30, 1758, to Humphry's younger brother, James Marshall and his wife, Sarah. Moses received an English and classical education, and from 1776 through 1779, he studied medicine in Wilmington, Delaware, under Dr. Nicholas Way. The Revolution, and particularly the nearby Battle of the Brandywine (1777), provided Moses a unique opportunity to sharpen his surgical skills. Moses soon abandoned his medical practice in favor of assisting his uncle in his expanding botanical and horticultural enterprise.
By late 1778, he was participating fully in his uncle's operations, assisting in locating, identifying, propagating, and shipping plant specimens, and he became quite a skilled "practical" botanist in his own right. His most significant contributions were in the preparation of Arbustrum Americanum, and the role he played on numerous exploring expeditions undertaken for the benefit of his uncle and their patrons. Moses appears to have taken great relish in these expeditions, and it was partly for his benefit that his uncle pressed scientific friends, including Franklin, Wistar, Jefferson (albeit indirectly), and members of the American Philosophical Society, to finance and organize a major expedition to the Missouri River region in 1785.
Moses' interest in botany appears to have waned by the mid-1790s. In 1796, Gov. Mifflin appointed him Justice of the Peace in Chester County, and his duties in this capacity occupied a great deal of his time. Moses' focus seems further to have shifted away from botany upon his marriage to Alice Pennock in 1797. The couple had six children. By the time of his uncle's death, Marshall had more or less washed his hands of the botanical and horticultural business, suggesting that he no longer had any time to fill orders for patrons and that his uncle's notes probably held little information of value to other botanists. Moses Marshall died in Philadelphia on October 13th, 1813.
Moses Marshall, Jr.
The life of Moses Marshall, Jr., is considerably less well known than that of his father or his great uncle. Moses, Jr., studied medicine in Philadelphia during the 1830s, and established a general practice in West Bradford shortly thereafter. Apparently he lectured publicly on scientific subjects, at least periodically, during the 1840s or 50s. Politically, Moses, Jr., aligned himself with the Democratic Party during the Civil War period, opposed actions to keep the South in the Union by force, and (unlike his mildly abolitionist great uncle), did not seem to consider slavery a major evil.
The collection is arranged into three series: "Correspondence, Writings, and Documents," "Poetry," and "Bound Materials."
The Humphry and Moses Marshall papers consist of 233 items: 181 letters (including drafts), 15 legal documents, 11 manuscripts, 10 poems, 4 account books, and several each of books, letter books, arithmetic notebooks, and broadsides. The materials span from 1721-1863.
The first series contains correspondence and a few legal documents and writings, arranged chronologically. The correspondence dates from 1733 to 1863 and is predominantly incoming. Humphry Marshall is the recipient of the bulk of the material (approximately 40%), followed by Moses Marshall (approx. 30%). The majority of the outgoing correspondence comes from the two "letterbooks" kept by Moses Marshall in 1791 and 1793. These books contain correspondence from a couple of days each, but provide a record of Marshall's response to inquiries from clients.
The bulk of correspondence prior to 1800 relates to Marshall's horticultural and botanical operations. Substantial numbers of orders are for plants and seeds from clients in other parts of the United States, England, Ireland, France, and Germany, and communications with middle men in the operation detail methods of packaging and shipping. Also of botanical interest is the correspondence with Marshall's "agents" in the field, including Moses Mendenhall, John and James Watson, Matthias King, Samuel Kramsh, and James Kenny. These men were admirers and friends of Humphry Marshall, and provided him with specimens collected from various regions of the country. The unsuccessful search for wild Franklinia alatamaha is mentioned in several letters (April 8, 1788: "There is not a plant of the Franklinia to be found"), and other letters include discussions of scientific expeditions either actualized or planned, mostly involving the participation of Moses Marshall. On November 14, 1786, Humphry described the logistics of tracking down ginseng, providing insight into the duties of plant collectors: "both of you being obliged to…encamp in the mountains strike up a fire & lie by it all night in the morning…climb up the sides of the mountains and dig towards evening…about 20 days in Going and Coming home again & digging the roots packing up &c." The content of the letters does not indicate the Marshalls' scientific interests or abilities, but this correspondence provides documentation for the complex network used by the Marshalls to collect, sell and distribute plants.
Approximately 18 letters relate to the Revolutionary War (see "Subject Index" under "Additional Descriptive Data"). These include letters that indicate Marshall's support for the nonimportation agreements (January 6, 1775), second hand reports of the Battles of Lexington and Concord (April 25, 1775) and of Yorktown (August 24, 1781), and an important series of correspondence from Samuel Preston Moore relating to the resignation of the trustees of the General Loan Office when American revolutionaries seized control (June 17 and 21, 1777). Also significant are two letters from Quaker conscientious objectors on the morality of paying taxes to support military activities (undated c. 1780 letter; July 14, 1781), a letter relating to the North Carolina Regulator insurrection (March 3, 1771), and one concerning the arrest by American forces of Quakers suspected of Loyalist sympathies (September 6, 1777). Finally, in the pre-Revolutionary period, the letters of James Kenny provide excellent descriptions of plant collecting and the area around Fort Pitt in 1759-60.
The items from 1840-1863 mainly relate to Moses Marshall, Jr. Most notable in among them are several letters from William Darlington written as he was preparing his Memorial to Humphry and Moses Marshall in 1848 and 1849. Moses, Jr's pro-Confederacy political views are clearly expressed in the series of three speeches written during the Civil War, also included in the series.
The Poetry series includes 10 undated poems. The Bound Materials series comprises the arithmetic notebooks of Jacob Martin, whose relationship to the Marshalls is unclear; Darlington’s manuscript, Historical Introduction to Bartram & Marshall, Marshall's copy of Dover's Useful Miscellanies; and nine uncut and unfolded sets of signatures from Arbustrum Americanum.
Subjects:
Botany--America.; Chester (Pa.); Fothergill, John, 1712-1780.; Franklinia.; Plant collectors.; Plants.; Quakers.; Science--History.; Trees.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783.; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783--Conscientious objectors.
Contributors:
Crèvecoeur, Michel-Guillaume Jean de, 1735-1813.; Darlington, William, 1782-1863.; Fothergill, Samuel, 1715-1772.; Kenny, James.; Martin, Jacob.; Mendenhall, Moses.; Moore, Samuel Preston, 1710-1785.; Watson, James.; Watson, John.
Genre Terms:
Field notes.; Legal documents.; Letters (correspondence); Memorial works.
- Correspondence, Writings, and Documents
  - [Luke Cock] Manuscript Copy Summary of a Sermon, 9mo 2d. 1721, "The substance of a Sermon publicly delivered at York in England by our Friend Luke Cock" (Box 1)
  - A[braham] M[arshall] and M[ary] M[arshall] ADS Copy to Samuel Marshall, May 2, 1733, Deed for land in Chester County.
  - Samuel Fothergill ALS to Ellen Evans, February 4, 1757, Fothergill sympathises with the loss of Evans' huband and advises her how best to cope
  - James Kenny ALS to Humphry Marshall, May 23, 1759, Botanical collecting in western Pennsylvania; Comments on Col. Hugh Mercer and the soldiers at Fort Duquesne; The Indians are glad to trade with Quakers for whom 'they profess a greater love & regard... than for any other amongst ye English'
  - Christopher AMs. Copy, June 30, 1759, Fragment of a manuscript.
  - Sam[ue]l Fothergill ALS Copy to Susannah Hatton, June 27, 1760, Advice to a woman about to depart on a mission to America
  - P. C_____n [Peter Collinson?] AMsS, ca. 1760, "Some Reflections on the Trial of Earl Ferrars"
  - James Kenny ALS to Humphry Marshall, June 7, 1761, Report on plants and animals in western Pennsylvania
  - James Kenny ALS to Humphry Marshall, December 6, 1761, Plants collected near Fort Pitt; Fort Pitt has been rebuilt in a more defensive posture
  - John Gibbons ALS to Humphry Marshall, December 26, 1767
  - Samuel Fisher ALS to Humphry Marshall, December 28, 1768
  - Moses Mendenhall ALS to Humphry Marshall, October 21, 1769, Mendenhall sends plant specimens from North Carolina and has made efforts to collect materials
  - H[enry] H[ale] Graham ALS to Humphry Marshall, December 25, 1769, Thanks for plants received
  - Joseph Williams and Nath[anie]l Pennock ADS to Catherine Wistar, December 22, 1770 - December 9, 1789, Loan of 200 pounds
  - Willi[am] Millikan ALS to Humphry Marshall, March 3, 1771, Account of the expulsion of Hermon Husbands from the North Carolina Assembly and the Regulator Insurrection
  - Hu[gh] Campbell ALS to Humphry Marshal[l], April 27, 1771, Thanks for plants and seeds received
  - John Marshall ALS to Humphry Marshall, August 14, 1771, and Joseph Storrs ALS to Humphry Marshall, August 28, 1771, Notes on Marshall's relatives in England
  - Joseph Shippen ALS to Humphry Marshall, January 12, 1773
  - H[enry] H[ale] Grah[am] ALS to Humphry Marshall (1722-1801), January 25, 1773, Congratulations on appointment as trustee to the General Loan Office
  - John Watts Manuscript Map, March 19, 1773, "Draught of the Fulling Mill Land in Lower Dublin which Richard Mathers conveyed to James Paul"
  - H[ugh] Campbell ALS to Humphry Marshall, April 19, 1773
  - AMs., [after May 15, 1773], "A Brief account of the last Sickness and Death of Esther Lewis"
  - Samuel Preston Moore ALS to Humphry Marshall, September 8, 1773, Meeting of the trustees of the General Loan Office
  - Hu[gh] Campbell ALS to Humphry Marshall, April 11, 1774, Receipt of nuts and seeds
  - James Marshall ADS, October 29, 1774, Last will and testament of James Marshall
  - John Gibbons ALS Copy to Humphry Marshall, January 2, 1775, and John Gibbons ALS to Humphry Marshall, February 16, 1775
  - Jno. Gibbons [John Gibbons] ALS to Humphry Marshall, January 6, 1775, Heavy losses by merchants to privateers. Hope for the success of the non-importation and non-exportation agreements
  - James Kenny ALS to Humphry Marshall, April 25, 1775, News that the King intends to arrest the members of Congress and all who write against the government; Trials of dissidents will be held in Admiralty Court with no evidence allowed other than their own writings. Rumor that persons of African descent will be given guns to rise against the Colonies. Battle near Boston
  - John Gibbons ALS to Humphry Marshall, August 7, 1775, Requests that Joseph Baker carry out some business for him. Ports in St. Eustatius may be closed
  - S[amuel] P[reston] Moore ALS to Humphry Marshall, February 7, 1777, and T[imoth]y Matlack ADS to Samuel Preston Moore, February 7, 1777, Order for the Trustees of the General. Loan Office to open "or they will answer the contrary at their peril"
  - Moses Mendenhall ALS to Humphry Marshall, May 13, 1777, Offer to collect plants for Marshall; Request for lima beans, juniper, etc.
  - S[amuel] P[reston] Moore ALS to Humphry Marshall, June 17, 1777, The General Assembly will draw out public monies held with the Loan Office
  - Sam[uel] Preston Moore ALS to [Humphry Marshall], June 21, 1777, Moore, as a trustee of the Loan Office, cannot follow the new laws as he is bound to obey the old. He therefore resigns and expects the other trustees to do likewise
  - S[amuel] P[reston] Moore ALS to Humphry Marshall, September 6, 1777, 15 or 16 Friends have been confined in the Free Masons' Lodge and will be removed to Staunton, Virginia.
  - T[homas] Bond ALS to Humphry Marshall, August 7, 1779, Mr. Gerard, the French minister, "wants our Curiosities and Novelties, we want his valuable Collections from all other Parts of the World"
  - T[homas] Bond ALS to Humphry Marshall, November 3, 1779, Bond has received plants for Mr. Gerard
  - T[homas] Bond ALS to Humphry Marshall, October 18, 1780, Gerard has not been heard from. Bond assumes 'his constant attention to the affairs of the Cabinet' is the reason
  - Th[omas] Bond ALS to Humphry Marshall, October 26, 1780, Noailles wishes to obtain plants for the Royal Garden in Paris. "They do not desire botanic curiosities, but such things only as would enrich France"
  - Th[omas] Bond ALS to Humphry Marshall, November 20, 1780, Bond favors Marshall's plan for reciprocal exchange of specimen with the French
  - Th[omas] Bond ALS to Humphry Marshall, December 2, 1780, Bond favors exchange of plants with Europeans
  - Anthony Benezet ALS to Humphry Marshall, [ca. 1780?], Thoughts on taxes to be used in support of the war: "The nature of the Gospel will not permit our giving either party and assistance in the... accomplishment of that horrid work"
  - Th[omas] Bond ALS to Humphry Marshall, March 16, 1781, Gerard wishes to continue their correspondence
  - Th[omas] Bond ALS to Humphry Marshall, April 6, 1781
  - Miers Fisher ALS to Humphry Marshall, April 18, 1781
  - Th[omas] Bond ALS to Humphry Marshall, July 2, 1781, Introduction for Gustavus Frederick Hilman, a Swedish naturalist
  - James Kenny ALS to Humphry Marshall, July 14, 1781, Comments on strife within the church and whether Friends should pay taxes to support the war
  - Th[omas] Bond ALS to Humphry Marshall, August 24, 1781, Hilman is working at Penn. Hospital. No prospect for peace. A large fleet will arrive, with Cornwallis as their object.
  - John Dickinson ALS to Humphry Marshall, November 7, 1781, Receipt and payment for seeds
  - James Marshall ADS to Moses Marshall, June 2, 1783, Power of attorney to reclaim possessions taken by the British at Brandywine
  - Geo[rge] Baker ALS to Humphry Marshall, December 12, 1783
  - John Gibbons ALS to Humphry Marshall, December 24, 1783, Will collect plants for Marshall in North Carolina
  - M[oses] Marshall ALS to Hum[phr]y Marshall, June 27, 1784, Description of plants seen and collected in central Pennsylvania. Has not collected shells or minerals
  - J. Logan ALS to Humphrey Marshall [Humphry Marshall], June 29, 1784
  - Geo[rge] Newsom ALS to Humphry Marshall, August 21, 1784, Few seeds received from Marshall have germinated
  - Geo[rge] Baker ALS to Humphry Marshall, August 28, 1784
  - Geo[rge] Newsom ALS to Humphry Marshall, April 21, 1785
  - Jno. Vaughan ALS to Humphry Marshall, May 5, 1785
  - Andrew Laffan ALS to Humphry Marshall, May 25, 1785, Request for plants
  - M[oses] Marshall ALS to Humphry Marshall, December 14, 1785
  - [Louis-Philippe-Joseph duc d' Orléans] Letter to [John Vaughan and Humphry Marshall?], [ca. 1785], Request for plants and seeds with instructions on how to prepare them for shipping. Letter written in French, translation present - possibly in the hand of William Temple Franklin, re: Ellen Cohen - Franklin Papers.
  - John Cummings ALS to Humphry Marshall, April 1, 1786, Cummings will try to fill Marshall's request for Southern seeds and plants. Request for plants. Severe weather has damaged his garden.
  - John Cummings ALS to Humphry Marshall, April 20, 1786
  - Mary Dickinson ALS to Humphry Marshall, June 12, 1786, Request for plants for an English friend
  - Geo[rge] Baker ALS to Humphry Marshall, September 13, 1786
  - Humphry Marshall ALS to Joseph Banks, November 14, 1786, Marshall and nephew have collected a large quantity of ginseng for Banks. Moses Marshall is available for Western exploration. Ginseng was collected under tough conditions 200 miles distant in the Alleghanies
  - John Cummings ALS to Humphry Marshall, March 20, 1787, Cummings has plants from South Carolina and Georgia for Marshall
  - Levis Janney ALS to Humphry Marshall, March 20, 1787, Janney has some cypress specimens
  - And[re]w Laffan ALS to Humphry Marshall, May 20, 1787, and Humphry Marshall AL Copy to Andrew Laffan, November 3, 1787, Acknowledgement of receipt of plants and order for more. Partial fulfilment of order
  - John Watson ALS to Humphry Marshall, October 1, 1787, With enclosures.
  - John Watson ALS to Humphry Marshall, October 23, 1787, More plants for Marshall and request from some in return; Franklinia is scarce and does not occur at all in Watson's area
  - John Watson ALS to Humphry Marshall, November 9, 1787, Request for fruit trees
  - St. John [Michel-Guillaume Jean de Crevecoeur] LS to Humphrey Marshall [Humphry Marshall], [before November 20], 1787, Wishes to see Marshall's catalogue and may be interested in purchasing plants for friends in France
  - St. John [Michel-Guillaume Jean de Crevecoeur] ALS to Humphrey Marshall [Humphry Marshall], November 20, [1787?], Has received Marshall's catalogue and wishes to know prices for seeds and plants
  - [Michel-Guillaume Jean de Crevecoeur] AL to [Humphry Marshall], [November 20, 1787?], List of plants and seeds desired for export to France. Includes notes on whether each species is common in France, how well each may grow there, and how to pack for shipment; See also Crevecoeur to Marshall, November 20, [1787?]
  - Jno. Vaughan [John Vaughan] ALS to Humphry Marshall, November 22, 1787, Bartram's catalog is longer and more varied than Marshall's
  - Comtesse de Tessé AL to [Humphry Marshall], [December 6, 1787], Request for plants and seeds; Instructions for preparing specimens for shipping
  - [Andrew Laffan] AL to Humphry Marshall, [ca. 1787], List of plants and seeds desired
  - John Watson ALS to Humphry Marshall, April 8, 1788, The search for wild Franklinia has proved fruitless